SECURITY RISK

BY POUL ANDERSON

Information was most certainly leaking. But the leak was not quite in the direction the Security force suspected....

I didn’t want to believe it of him. In his quiet way, Sherman was one of the most beloved men in the Project. But you can’t tell, you can’t ever look behind the mask which is flesh. I remembered Horn from years ago: another pleasant man, who shared my fondness for Siamese cats. And he had been slipping information to the Communists.

In an age of chaos, when today’s stout ally is tomorrow’s wolf at your throat, it’s hard to know where your loyalties lie. My own were clear enough, for the enemy had landed in California and my parents lived there if they still lived at all. But I don’t presume to weigh another man’s soul; I catch him and bring him to trial, and the final judgment is not for mortal men.

Walker leaned back and lit another cigarette. The vile wartime tobacco crept in smoke across the desk to sting my nostrils. "Of course," he said, "we don’t know Sherman is guilty of anything but a small technical breach of regulations. All we’ve established is that he takes certain papers to his room at night."

"Maybe just to study them?" I ventured hopefully.

"He could do that in his own office. Those papers aren’t supposed to leave the main laboratory, Harkness. Not ever."

"Distractions, around here," I said. "Wrong environment. Research is a high art, sir. And artists occasionally need the right surroundings if they’re to accomplish anything."

"That may be," admitted Walker.

"It’s hard to see how he could communicate with anyone outside. If it is only as you suggest, only that he wants privacy to think about the stuff . . . well, I daresay we can wink at his flouting the regs. But if that’s all, why hasn’t he asked me if he could? Why so secretive about it? The sole reason we know he’s doing it is . . . well, I just told you."

I nodded, reluctantly. Bassington had wanted data on alloy properties at midnight—his gang often worked around the clock—and had gone to the secret file. The folder he needed was missing. The next morning it was back in place. He reported the matter to Security, and a quiet check revealed that only Sherman could have removed it. Since then he had been watched, and it had happened every night. Now I was being assigned to find out why and, if necessary, to arrest Sherman whom I liked.

"He doesn’t have any idea you’re in Security, does he?" asked Walker.

"Not as far as I know, sir. I am a physicist too, working over in Propellants."

"All right. You’re hereby transferred to Explosives."

"That’ll be hard to explain, won’t it? I mean, the missile to deliver the bomb Isn’t too closely related to the bomb itself."

"Precisely," answered Walker. There was a thin smile on his mouth. "You’ll have every bit as hard a time explaining it as Sherman is going to have explaining why lie, in Explosives, wants data from the rocket section."

At that, we didn’t need a very elaborate cover story. After all, the missile and its warhead had to be engineered into one unit. A certain amount of liaison between the two main divisions of the Project was necessary.

As a matter of fact, we had found that work went faster if we didn’t erect more than a very low wall of secrecy between our different branches. A man working on the aiming mechanism of the bomb could often stimulate his own thinking, get a fresh viewpoint, by talking his problem over with, say, a fellow developing the "brain” which would steer the rocket. Both jobs were electronic. So people mingled rather freely inside the Project.

Of course, they never got outside it. They never would, till the war ended or till a hostile bomber found us and flattened us. Nobody went in or out of the high fence except a few top officers, and they were always under the eyes of a military guard, day and night.

With the enemy holding most of Asia and the Pacific, ramping through Afghanistan toward Europe and building a bridgehead on the American West Coast, it was a small sacrifice. If the Project succeeded in time, we would probably win the war. If it did not, or if the enemy learned about it and destroyed it, we would certainly lose. Things were as simple as that.

I walked up the steps of the so-called bombproof and into the sleazy shack which camoflaged it Green, wooded hills, rolled morning sunlight, with here and there another hut disguising a ventilator or a garage or an entrance. Everything which mattered had burrowed into the Earth, and the trees hid the electric fence and the tramping sentries.

Standing there among wildflowers, under tall white ranks of cumulus, 1 knew a moment when it was hard to believe that here free men stood with their backs to the wall while the anthill civilization of a conquered Asia grew daily higher beyond this sunlit horizon. Then a jet squadron whistled overhead, eastbound to some battle over the Atlantic, and I remembered.

I went to the pseudo-greengrocer’s of our pseudo-hamlet and down another flight of steps and along a corridor coldly lit by fluorescents. The air smelled dank. A pair of technicians trundled a bottle of liquid oxygen past me, and doors stood open on a bustle of smocked figures and a jumble of apparatus, but somehow I felt very much alone.

I found Sherman in his own lab. He nodded vaguely at me and continued giving directions to an assistant. The fellow took notes obediently enough, but I didn’t miss the look of surprise on his face.

"All right,” said Sherman, after a longish while. "Set that up, run it through the computer, and get me the answers day before yesterday, if not sooner.”

"But the others—”

Sherman went to a desk and scribbled something on official stationery. "Here. This gives you top priority. Bump everybody else. Leap!"

The man stood there for just a second, then took the paper and walked swiftly out between looming generators. Sherman turned to me and thrust out his hand. I took it.

"Hullo, Harkness," he said. "I understood you were being transferred over here. Didn’t expect you so soon."

He was a medium-sized man, with untidy clothes and untidy brown hair above a wide, snub-nosed face. He looked tired and, somehow, harried. It was hard to see in him one of the foremost of that stupefying plunge into the mathematics of space, time, and energy which has given us an entire new cosmos to think about. Or to see in him a traitor. But—

"What’s the reason?" he asked. He took out a stubby, charred pipe. "Co-ordination wasn’t very clear about it. Glad to have you, of course"—hitherto we had only met socially—"but I really don’t need any extra help.”

"We do, though," I said. My lie was prepared, I delivered it easily. "You see, we’re getting to a stage where we have to know the exact mass and dimensions of the warhead to go any further. It would help, too, if we knew something about the way it will be connected to the rest of this hell’s engine—safety circuits, for instance."

"I see." Sherman opened his tobacco pouch, scowling. "Didn’t realize you were that far along. A rocket able to go halfway around the world—it can’t be dreamed up overnight!"

"We had all the experience of World War II and the so-called peacetime research,” I pointed out. "At any rate, Co-ordination thought it would be a good idea for me to work with you a few days and get some insight into your end of the Project.”

"It’s in the reports,” he said irritably, tamping his bowl.

"Not the same thing at all. You know that. Engineering is a matter of ... of feel . . . especially when we’re so close to the end.”

"I see,” he repeated. He made an elaborate business of lighting the pipe. "Yes. Though I’m really a theoretical man, y’know, not an engineer at all. I look at the problem from a broad analytic standpoint and let the other chaps worry about the details."

"All right,” I snapped, losing patience. "I know all that. But let’s have some details."

"I’m afraid they won’t be available for a while.” Sherman looked past me.

"What?”

"It’s a new approach." He spoke eagerly, but still didn’t meet my eyes. "An entirely different reaction —perhaps a million times the energy release of the one we had in mind.”

I stood very quiet.

"It has to be studied out,” he said in an urgent tone. "Those data I just gave Smedley to put through the computer—they’ll give me some inkling as to whether we can do it or not. If we can . . . don’t you see, Harkness? We won’t have to build a thousand missiles. A hundred at the most—fifty, I think—will end the war!”

"Assuming this works,” I muttered slowly.

"I’m quite sure it will. It’s worth investing a few weeks to find out, isn’t it?”

I had a sudden thought which stopped my heart for an instant. There was more than one way to sabotage the Project!

God knew how many thousands of highly skilled man-years had gone into the present bomb, the one we meant to use. Atomic energy is still such a new field. A false lead, one which would send us all up a blind alley for a year or more—and meanwhile the enemy roared across the Sierras and through Suez.

Sherman caught my arm. "Harkness! What’s wrong?”

"Nothing,” I mumbled. "Overwork.”

I reined myself in. The job had suddenly grown immensely bigger. Big enough to frighten me, big enough to overshadow the entire planet.

There was just one way I could see to do my task. I had to get Sherman’s confidence. He was only a man, I told myself, only a man, neither devil nor god nor cloak- and-dagger conspirator by nature. If he dropped a single careless hint to me, it would serve.

I was going to have a hard time becoming his friend. The agony which had been New York, San Francisco, Bandung, Capetown, a score of cities yelled to a smoking sky for revenge. And I must break bread with a man who might be working for their murderers.

"Well,” I said, "my orders still stand. Maybe I can even help.”

"Maybe you can, at that,” he said disarmingly. "You'll have picked up a good bit of first-hand information about alloys over in Propellants, and this job may call for some very special alloys.” He glanced at his watch. "It’s nearly time for lunch. I don’t like the cafeteria. Let’s go to my place and have some sandwiches and talk it over.”

As a bachelor, Sherman had only one small room. He had fixed it up in the past couple of years so it had become almost an extension of himself: a trifle dusty, books heaped everywhere, two abstract paintings on the wall, a desk littered with bescrawled sheets of paper. He put water on to boil and broke out tinned meats and a ripe cheese, talking all the while.

The reaction he had in mind was awesome enough. If it did work, then it would, in soberest truth, end the war. But I knew how many theoretical possibilities never materialize in time to do much good.

"It'll take a lot of engineering,” I objected. "Just suppose it is practicable. It’ll still take us longer to make it work, , work efficiently enough for military purposes, than to wind up the original Project.”

“No,” said Sherman. “No, if that were the case, of course I wouldn’t waste time, on it. But—it may be simpler than you think. I may be able to give Co-ordination a full set of blueprints in a few weeks . . . perhaps they can have it built, tested, and in use before New Year’s!”

I whistled. This was too fantastic to swallow. “I thought you said you weren’t an engineer,” I objected feebly.

"I’m not. I’m a theoretical physicist. But this problem . . . oh, rot, I'd have to spend three years educating you before you could see what I mean. Let’s just say it’s, uh, unusually susceptible to analysis.”

That was a lie. Sherman was not a good liar, I could see the flush go up his cheeks and he got abnormally busy with his sandwiches. I felt cold.

“How did you get the idea?” I asked.

“It’s nothing new, really. The reaction has been known for a long time; the problem was to generate it on a sufficiently large scale. I . . . I got to thinking about it. I’m still only in the thinking stage, actually: that’s why I haven’t yet filed any official report about this. But all I ask is a few more weeks.”

“You do quite a varied bit of thinking,” I remarked. My eyes wandered across the bookshelves. “I see you’re still interested in this extrasensory business.”

That had been in his dossier, the somewhat crankish preoccupation with telepathy, telekinesis, precognition, a shadow domain about whose very existence the scientists couldn’t agree. But his work in physics had been too blindingly brilliant for us to look closely at so small a fault.

Or was it small? I wondered. A mind attracted to such mysticism might easily be sucked down by the quasi-religious ideology of the enemy. Freedom is, above all, a state of the practical mind, the natural condition of sober men among sober realities; the pomp and glitter of, let us say, a Coronation in London is only froth above the daily routine of parliamentary government. It is the tyrants who make everything into an ecstatic rite.

“Yes.” Sherman turned around, his eyes kindling. “Yes, you know, there is something there. I’ve experienced it, felt other minds touching mine—” He shook his head, wryly. “Trouble is, there seem to be very few people who can have the experience. Whether that’s due to some inborn difference, or only, to conditioning, I don’t know. But the fact remains. I can perform an ESP experiment to my own satisfaction, but I can’t reproduce it for a disinterested audience. They’d only see me lying in a kind of Hindu trance. If they tried it themselves, doing exactly as I did, nothing would happen.”

“Interesting question.” I remembered I had to win his trust, and for a man like this the best way to do it was to talk about his own hobbyhorses. "Reproducibility is the characteristic of science. If every competent observer can’t check an assertion for himself, it isn’t acceptable. And yet—"

"Yet there are experiments in the real world which are not reproducible." Sherman piled sandwiches on a plate and poured water into the coffeepot. "You yourself are one, you know. You exist, but there’s no known way to create another, identical Simon Harkness. Modern physics is full of such propositions: consider the uncertainty principle."

"Uh, yes." I took a sandwich. "Isn’t there something in your own work, your mathematical work before the war, I mean, on the same order?"

"You mean the parallel universes." Sherman grinned at me, but there was something else above the humor, a tension— "That was the one the newspapers made such a sensation about."

"Well, it was sensational enough."

"Merely a sideline," said Sherman. He whispered, as if to himself, and there was pain in the whisper: "Then." After a moment: "An incidental consequence of the definition of change of state I had to adopt to account for . . . well, look it up yourself sometime. An electron, or any other particle, has only a certain probability of being where it is, to speak Irishly. In principle, it could be anywhere in the universe. From my definition, it follows that the particle is anywhere. It’s both here and in Japan and on Mars and in the farthest star—every possible configuration of every existing particle of matter or energy. Each configuration represents a complete universe. Throw in the time variable, and you have a complete set of continua, from origin to extinction."

"I remember that," I said. "But isn’t the joker that, well, you can’t test this theory? That there’s no possible physical interaction between these different configurations?"

"That’s right," he nodded. "By definition, almost. If there were interaction, if a particle went from Configuration A to Configuration B, they wouldn’t be A and B any longer."

He looked at his paintings. "But of course," he said, so low I could barely hear it, "the mind is not a structure but a pattern. It isn’t physical."

And then he would say no more. He switched the talk back to practicalities, throwing himself into the details of what I could do to help. It was as if he were trying to escape something.

As the head of his department, Sherman necessarily had broad discretionary powers. He could hold up work for a few days while he fiddled with his esoterica, But not much longer.

After a week, I seized a chance to speak with Walker. "Tell Co-ordination to have patience," I urged. "Give him . . . me . . . a bit more time.”

My chief scowled at the wall which penned him underground. "Why?” he said. "Either the man has a genuine lead, in which case he should make a definite report and recommendations now—not when he happens to feel like it—or he’s leading us up the garden path.” He swung on me, savagely. "And in that case—d’you think he’s doing it deliberately?”

"I don’t know,” I said. "I just don’t know.”

"Well—”

"But he’s had us making tests with the proton accelerator. And he’s hogging the computer, having equations solved that he just hands to the personnel without a word of explanation. Does he pull them out of his head? Even Sherman can’t be that gifted. And yet, those tests and computations he orders are not mere fakery. They make good physical sense. Only yesterday, we proved that this reaction really will take place on the scale we need.”

"There’s still all the engineering work,” said Walker. "It could tie us up for years. We know our present bombs can be made, and that they’ll hurt the enemy badly.”

"If Sherman’s bomb works, we’ll know more than that,” I said. "We’ll know with absolute certainty that we’re going to win. The Project as it stands right now can’t guarantee that. The enemy has underground installations too you realize. Sherman’s bomb will get those, ours won’t.”

"Ours will break their cities open like rotten eggs.”

"And perhaps make them all the angrier. They can live better off the country than we can. We aren’t going to be sure of pulling their teeth unless we can smash their deepest-buried factories—or sink their biggest task force with one missile.” It was as delicate a problem as men had ever faced. The aerial annihilation of the war’s early phase had ended: bomber-killing rockets became too effective, and neither side had yet developed a missile with more than fifteen hundred miles range. Our intercontinental atomic torpedo would redress that situation, but unless it carried the Sherman bomb it might not tip the scales enough.

"All right,” said Walker. "But if he really is sincere,”—his finger stabbed at me—"why is he taking those plans and data on the antipodal rocket home with him every night? That doesn’t hook in with his new research, does it?”

"No,” I admitted. "And still—” "What?”

"Call it a hunch. If I told you how often I’ve played hunches, you’d give me the sack this minute. And yet I have a pretty good record in the Secret Service.”

"You think he really is on our side, then?”

"No,” I said. "Not entirely. I get the impression of . . . of divided loyalties. As if ... I don’t know. I couldn’t tell you who is sharing his loyalty.”

Walker riffled the dossier on his desk, though he must have learned it by heart. "He was tied up with the World Culture League before the war, and that was an enemy front,” he said. "As far as we could tell, he was innocently involved, and got out as soon as he discovered the truth about them. But—”

"But what’s he doing with those rocket data?” I finished.

"'Nevertheless—” Walker got up and paced the floor, heavily. "See here, Harkness. Let’s assume he is a spy. How does he transmit the information?”

The stillness grew cavernous.

Walker whirled on me. "I say, what’s the matter? See a ghost?”

"Maybe,” I whispered.

"What is it, man? For God’s sake!”

"Don’t ask me to tell you. Not yet. I don’t really believe it myself.” My words stumbled past each other. "Look, chief, can you have him called on the carpet tonight? It’d be easy enough. Co-ordination is champing at the bit. Have Sir Hugo call him in and ask what the hell he thinks he’s doing. Detain him for a couple of hours.”

"And meanwhile you search his quarters?” Walker grinned harshly. "My dear fellow, it’s been done twice already.”

"Maybe the other people didn’t know what to look for,” I said.

I could not help feeling a certain guiltiness. Sherman had opened himself to me—not much, but more than to any others. There was that curious attraction between us which arises among some men and makes them glad to be together.

Not that we exchanged confidences. We simply lost a degree of shyness, and were not afraid to be enthusiastic. I listened to him burble about his hunting lodge on Lake Superior; yes, I must come up there after the war, and he heard me rave about my Siamese tom. We shared a fondness for Bach and—oh, many things.

Now and then he touched on his ESP, but shied back from it like a startled horse. It was the great thing in his life, greater even than his mathematics, but when it broke forth he curbed himself, queerly afraid of saying too much.

And once, when we had worked very late and crackled a bottle of whisky and been hit rather harder by it than we expected, he had said something about a woman, the only woman alive for him, but he could not have her, not ever— He shut that off, too, as if a barrier had clanked home. I guessed he was in love with someone else’s wife. Poor devil! It turned out to be worse than that.

So while he sweated under the Oxonian whiplash of Sir Hugo’s tongue, I stole down the buried corridors and unlocked his room with a master key.

There’s an art to searching a place without leaving spoor. I devoted myself to it for an hour, finding little. The forbidden papers were on a table by his couch: blueprints of the fuel-feed system, this time. Nearby was a stack of virgin sheets and a drafting board with its tools, so arranged that he could lie on the couch and make drawings—of what ?

I had a rather grisly thought. Suppose the bomb was not a fake, after all. Suppose it would actually work—and we built one, and since we wouldn't be familiar with all the details, he could touch it off here.

But it didn’t make sense! A complete atomic bomb represents the efforts of thousands of specialists. Sherman couldn’t hold all that knowledge, not in one human skull.

(Martians? Homo Superior? Dismiss them; if that was the case, the game was already lost.)

No, I thought bleakly, the bomb must be history’s most gigantic hoax, plausible enough to gain him the time he needed. And that time, at night, was spent sending to the enemy the data which American and British skill had piled up through laborious years. Learning all we had learned, as a free gift, the enemy could have our missiles built before we did.

No hidden wireless, no whispered messages, no copied papers passed from hand to furtive hand. Telepathy—

I looked at the calendar. In this summer of 1958 might befall the end of Earth’s only civilization built on freedom under the law.

Concealment! He would be back soon. I went under the couch. It was dusty there, I wanted to sneeze. The gun seemed to glide of itself from my pocket to my hand.

If Sherman was sending to the enemy by telepathy, it would be hard to prove. But if he lay on this couch, in the typical trance, scanning the papers with blind blank eyes, that would be enough for me.

A key snicked in the lock. Almost, I jerked.

I saw only his feet. They moved wearily. I saw that the heels of his shoes were run down, and somehow that was infinitely pathetic. He locked the door behind him and shuffled across to the hotplate and started some coffee.

I waited. My belly muscles drew taut. It had been a long day, and now I would be spending the night beneath this settee, till he had gone again—dust was acrid in my nose, my eyelids drooped, I snapped them up with an effort.

He took his time, maddeningly. The smell of coffee was pure torment. He took off his clothes, donned pajamas and bathrobe; he lit his pipe and sat for a while reading.

An hour dragged. My watch glowed at me, it blurred ... it was nearly midnight! Wasn’t he going to do anything?

The slippered feet neared the couch. Sherman’s weight forced the ancient springs down, one of them dug into my shoulders. I made myself flatter.

I heard him adjusting pillows, seeking a comfortable position. I heard the rustle of papers in his hands. He reached out and snapped down the electric switch, darkness thundered into the room. For a moment, only the whine of the ventilator talked.

Then he turned on a desk lamp which stood on his table. I judged it was focused on the papers, one spot of luminance in a world gone to night. I heard him muttering to himself, it sounded almost like an incantation . . . autohypnosis . . . get his mind into the right state . . . my own soul followed, willy-nilly. My head drooped, my eyelids weighed a ton. A crazy whirl went through my brain, the disconnected half-dreams of pre-sleep. King's Cross and green hats and trees blowing in an April wind and the wide cosmos multiplied—

"... Are you there, my darling?”

I jerked awake. The voice snapped out of my consciousness.

Sherman lay quiet, speaking no more. Or had he spoken? It had been his voice, but somehow not his voice—no mere sound pattern could have carried that unlimited tenderness.

I stared stupidly at my watch. Enough light trickled down from the lamp to blot out its luminosity. But the face, the face, its numbers crawled and intertwined like snakes, I slid down a long black incline toward sleep.

“. . . Hurry. No time to be human.”

I saw the woman, I saw her, I swear. She was tall and blond, she wore a nightgown of almost indecent cut but she wore it naturally, as if she had never heard of another mode. She lay on a bed in a room where the only light fell on her hands. There were blueprints in her hands. The room smelt faintly of lavender.

”. . . Why, my darling? There are hours until morning!”

Sherman answered her, bleakly:

”. . . Sir Hugo called me in. He wanted to know—they’re getting suspicious. I shall have to give them something definite, or find myself arrested for treason. Do you need my data immediately?”

” . . Not yet. It can wait.”

”. . . Then I won’t send you anything tonight—except all my love. I’ll copy everything you have there. It should be enough to gain me a reprieve.”

”. . It will take days to copy everything.”

”. . Let me have the days, then! Every hour my countrymen are dying.”

”. . . (Our case is not so urgent. There is no open war yet. If you can give me what you know, and They —the chiefs, the officials, the blind blundering brass—can only be persuaded it’s genuine, there may never be a war.)

”... I hope not, O I hope not. If Thou wert to stand in the fire-sleet—”

”... Here. Here is Sheet One.”

Her face faded. White-on-blue intricacy rose before me. Somewhere, immensely removed, I heard the scratching of Sherman’s pencil. He was copying, line for line, with a precision impossible to a waking man.

It was a mechanical thing. It took most of his mind, but not quite all, a thread of endearments wove between the hard lines. I would not want to live through such longing again.

And the hours went by. Somewhere above us the sun rose, and unshaven men on muddy earth heard artillery crash in disputed hills.

”. . . That is the end for this night. I have to go.”

”. . . I, too. I hate the mornings!”

My brain crawled back to wakefulness.

Sherman lay for a while, breathing hard. Then, very slowly, like an old man, he got up.

I should, perhaps, have waited till he was gone. I had no authority to do otherwise. But hunches—there are people with a bit, just a bit of ESP. I had been able to listen tonight; I knew better, now, where my hunches came from.

Sherman went into the shower cubicle. I heard water rushing. It covered the small noise I made getting from beneath the couch.

When he came back, I sat there looking at his drawings.

He stood still for a moment.

"Where is she?” I asked.

”You were here.” He said it in a dead voice.

''Yes.” I ruffled the papers. "I see this is only a part of it. How long do you think it’ll take to get the rest?”

He shambled toward me, his eyes were red and there was a twitching in one cheek. "What right did you have?” he whispered.

"Secret Service,” I told him. "Your actions were pretty suspicious.”

"In God’s name,” he screamed, "I’m going to win the war for you! Ill have the complete plans inside a week. It’ll take perhaps three months to test everything and start production. In less than a year, the enemy will be smashed! Isn’t that enough? Do you have to stick your filthy nose into my private life as well?”

"Sorry, old chap.” I laid my gun on the table, but not too far from my hand. "I didn’t like this job, but— Suppose you explain. If it satisfies me, perhaps my superiors won’t have to know every detail.”

"I didn’t want them to know any part of it,” he croaked. "Not just that it’s . . . personal. But d’you think they’d have believed? They’re none of them esp-sensitive.”

"Right,” I admitted. "You’d have been in the loony hatch long ago if— When did it start?”

Sherman sat down, listlessly, staring at his knees. "About a year ago. I was still experimenting with my ESP, don’t you know, in what spare time I had—trying for clairaudience. I contacted her, mind to mind. It was just an occasional flicker at first.

We only mastered the technique fully last month.”

"And where is she?”

"In America. She’s an American, the same as you and me. Only it’s a different America, in one of my parallel universes. I suppose . . . I suppose knowing the mathematics of it helped me contact her . . . that, and a sort of autohypnotic state—”

"I fell three-fourths asleep under the couch,” I said. "I, uh, listened in . . . couldn’t help it . . . inductive effect? I seem to have a small degree of ESP myself, not as much as you but enough to— What kind of world does she live in?”

The knowledge had drained me of feeling. I could only speak dry words in a dry voice, like a man seeing the Grand Canyon by moonlight for the first time.

Something of life returned to Sherman. He couldn’t hate me, not entirely, when I gave him the chance to talk about this thing which had been throttled inside him.

"It isn’t very alien to our universe,” he said. "The particles of the two Earths didn’t assume a significantly different configuration till, oh, about one hundred eighty years ago. The death of George Washington by a sniper’s bullet— But they’re a free people there, too. English parliamentary democracy just had to evolve along much the same lines, whatever happened.”

He sighed. "Still, there are some important variations. They’re ahead of us in atomics, we’re ahead in rocketry. So don’t you see, Harkness? Don’t you see? I’ve been giving her data on our missile, and she’s been telling me about their bomb. In both worlds, the free countries can have the ultimate weapon!”

I had no quick reply. I went instead to his coffeepot and started making up a brew. We needed it badly, with brandy.

"I believe you, of course,” I said at last. "After hearing your thoughts —but it is a gross breach of security.”

"How?” he protested. ’They can’t menace us, no matter what happens. I told you, my theory shows beyond doubt, that all physical Interaction is impossible. Only the mind, which is not physical at all, can touch—”

And a poor devil can fall in love with a woman he can never have. But there was no reason to speak of that.

"Since I’d have only my bare word to support your story, we’d better spin a yarn which will satisfy the right people,” I said. "Convince ’em you are a super-genius—that in some way your ESP work has completely integrated your conscious and subconscious minds. Yes, I think we can do it.”

"I’ll have me a time living up to that sort of reputation,” said Sherman. "But what the hell?”

Over coffee, then, he told me what he had learned of this other Earth. It was an eerie thing to listen to. When I laid the histories side by side, I saw what a thin chain of accidents and miracles man's life must be.

Earth One: The American colonial revolution succeeded, American became a republic—minus Canada— and even fought on the side of Napoleon, 1812-14; later she had a civil war over the slavery issue, which Britain had settled more quietly, but still expanded to the Pacific and beyond. She became the refuge of discontented European liberals in the Nineteenth Century, an inspiration to the world. Meanwhile Germany was unified, and took Alsace-Lorraine from France in 1870, thus planting the seeds of the First World War, 1914-18, in which Russia went under and became a prey to Communism. America was a belated British ally in that war and in the second one, 1939-45, when an embittered Germany and a rampant Japan had to be defeated. Russia was on the Anglo-Saxon side then, but turned against the democracies immediately afterward.

Earth Two: The American rebellion collapsed soon after George Washington’s death in 1778; but Lord North and his kind applied the lesson, colonial government improved until the Dominion of North America was created. With troops from the Western Hemisphere to help—as well as to overrun French and Spanish possessions nearer home— Napoleon was crushed by 1812 and monarchy was firmly reestablished. This left the Nineteenth-Century German liberals no place to go, they stayed home and their influence speeded unification; there was a Franco-Prussian war in 1860, and a French revanche with British help in World War I, 1898-1904. It was that long and bloody a struggle because machine guns were available but not yet tanks and airplanes. By the same token, though, Russia was relatively less backward, survived the German onslaught but remained weak and corrupt. A devastated Germany went Communist, rebuilt, and the Second World War lasted from 1930-1935, till the Teuton fury was finally quenched. Russia, whipped by the Germans and under a puppet Red regime during the war, was easy game for Britain’s Pacific ally, Japan, which grabbed off substantial Russian and Chinese territories. Afterward, an exhausted British Empire faced a vigorous Japan using the new tide of Asiatic nationalism as a lever against the white man.

Yes, it made a grim kind of sense. Both histories did.

But strange to think that one world had already had its war with Japan and that Russia, the amiable bumbling Russian Republic, was the deadly Communist menace of its 1958, and in that world they could build a hydrogen bomb while the other played with uranium but stood ten years ahead in rocketry.

Security or no, it was a good bargain Sherman had made!

I bade him adieu for now and went upstairs. For a moment I stood in the doorway of the camouflage house, beneath the King’s portrait. It was just sunrise and the Union Jack was being raised, brave above the hills of Kentucky.

THE END